<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Kings Maiestie at White-Hall vpon the ninth of Februarie. 1605. By the Reuerend Father in God, Anthonie Rudd, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of Saint Dauids</title>
            <title>Sermon preached before the Kings Majestie at White-Hall upon the ninth of February. 1605.</title>
            <author>Rudd, Anthony, 1549 or 50-1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12417</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12417)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1582:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Kings Maiestie at White-Hall vpon the ninth of Februarie. 1605. By the Reuerend Father in God, Anthonie Rudd, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of Saint Dauids</title>
                  <title>Sermon preached before the Kings Majestie at White-Hall upon the ninth of February. 1605.</title>
                  <author>Rudd, Anthony, 1549 or 50-1615.</author>
                  <author>T. S., fl. 1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Humfrey Lownes, for Clement Knight,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: T.S.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴(-E4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12417:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON Preached before the Kings Maieſtie at White-<hi>Hall vpon the ninth of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie.</hi> 1605.</p>
            <p>By the Reuerend Father in God, <hi>Anthonie Rudd,</hi> Doctor in Diuinitie, <hi>and Lord Biſhop of Saint</hi> Dauids.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>Humfrey Lownes,</hi> for <hi>Clement Knight.</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12417:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12417:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing gotten the Coppie of this Sermon heere following and read it ouer once or twiſe, I thought it not vnmeete to aduenture to publiſh it for the common good of others, which ſhall vouchſafe to pervſe it. <hi>Febr. 26. 1605.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord. T. S:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12417:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12417:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME. 3.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Saluation belongeth vnto the Lord, and thy bleſſing is vpon thy people.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme was <hi>Dauids</hi> meditation, when he was forced to flie before his vnnaturall Sonne <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> who tooke vp armes to depriue him of the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, and mightily for a time preuailed againſt him.</p>
            <p>Heerein firſt hee falleth into an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of the great number of his enemies conſpiringe his deſtruction, but falſely perſwadinge themſelues that
<pb facs="tcp:12417:4"/>
God had forſaken him: Verſ. 1.2. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he expreſſeth what confidence he put in God, and what aſſurance he had by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the aſſaults and attempts of his aduerſaries. verſ. 3.4.5.6. Thirdly, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth petition for helpe, grounding his hope vpon Gods former protection: Verſ. 7, Fourthly, he concludeth the Pſalme with this Epiphonema: Saluation belongeth vnto the Lord, and thy bleſſing is vppon thy people, Verſe 8: In which words hee aſcribeth vnto the Lord the power of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them which be in peril, and that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereby he prouideth for the ſafetie of his people, and heapeth vppon them innumerable benefits and bleſſings:</p>
            <p>Now imagin with me, that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſitting aloft in his Chaire of eſtate looketh downe to his ſubiects ſaying, Saluation belongeth vnto the Lord: And then caſting vppe his eyes to Heauen, by an Apoſtrophe to God ſaith thus. And thy bleſſing is vppon thy people. When <hi>Jonas</hi> had cried out of the belly of Hell, and the Lord had heard his voice,<note place="margin">Ionae, 2.2.6.9.</note> and brought his life from the pit, then he pronounced definitiuely that Saluation
<pb facs="tcp:12417:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is of the Lord. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> had conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered aduiſedly of martial affaires from the beginning to the ending thereof,<note place="margin">Prou. 21.31.</note> he reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely concluded, that the horſe is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the day of battaile, but Saluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is of the Lord.</p>
            <p>By Saluation heere, is vnderſtood tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall preſeruation from worldly troubles and perils: of the which <hi>I</hi> expound that in the 36 Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſa, 36 6.</note> Thou Lord dooſt ſaue man and beaſt. And thereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, when he ſaith to <hi>Timothie,</hi> that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God,<note place="margin">1 Tim, 4.10.</note> is the Sauiour of all men, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of thoſe that beleeue.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that Saluation is of the Lord, vaine is the hope of them, that without, or againſt God, put their truſt in any worldly meanes. When <hi>Pharaoh</hi> purſued the <hi>Jſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> he repoſed his vndoubted hope of victorie in his Chariots, Horſes, and great Hoſte of valiant armed men: but when the Lord came forth as a man of warre againſt him, then he and all his were caſt into the Sea, the deepthes couered them,<note place="margin">Exod. 14. &amp; 15.3.4.5.</note> and they ſanke to the bottom as a ſtone. Who will ſet vp his reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> huge bignes &amp; ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:12417:5"/>
of bodie, after that the <hi>Anakims</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed vnder the conduct of <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 11.21.22. 1. Sam. 17.50.51 &amp;. 2. Sam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.15.40. To the end.</note> and <hi>Goliah</hi> with the other ſonnes of <hi>Haraphah</hi> fell by the hands <hi>Dauid,</hi> and his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies? Leagues with forraine Princes are but a broken ſtaffe of reede without the Lord, for that wee read of the <hi>Edomites</hi> in <hi>Obadiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obad. verſe 7.</note> that the men of their confederacie drave them to the borders. As for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and treaſures,<note place="margin">Prouerbs. 11.4</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> hath giuen this verdit of them,<note place="margin">Prouerb, 23.5.</note> that they auaile not in the day of wrath: but euen when men ſhould ſtand in greateſt neede of them, then they take them to their winges as an Eagle and flie vnto the Heauens. Food and victuals are neceſſarie for the ſuſtentation of mans life:<note place="margin">Ezech 4.16. Amos. 4 6.</note> but God in his anger can eaſily break the ſtaffe of bread, and giue cleanneſſe of teeth in all our Citties. If fortifications would haue ſerued the turn, then might the <hi>Cananites</hi> haue beene ſafe in their Cities,<note place="margin">Deut 9.1.</note> which were great &amp; walled vp to Heauen. What can Counſell, pollicie &amp; wordly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, effecte of themſelues,<note place="margin">Iob. 12 20.</note> ſeeing that <hi>Job</hi> hath obſerued that God taketh (at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) ſpeech from the Counſellers, and
<pb facs="tcp:12417:5"/>
iudgement from the auncient. And this is one of <hi>Salomons Maximaes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21.30.</note> that there is no wiſedome, neither vnderſtanding, nor Counſell againſt the Lord. In the time of ſickeneſſe, without the Lord nothing auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Phiſitian, as in the cauſe of <hi>Aſa;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 2. king. 1.1.2.</note> nor yet the God of <hi>Ekron,</hi> as in the caſe of <hi>Azariah.</hi> And that we may know that noe mortall man, nor all the ſonnes of men put together can ſaue vs without the Lorde, therefore wee are aduiſed by the Prophet <hi>Jſay</hi> to ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the man whoſe breath is in his Noſtrelles:<note place="margin">Iſay. 2.22.</note> for wherein is hee to bee eſteemed?<note place="margin">Ionae. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Jonas</hi> hath vttered all this in fewe wordes, ſaying: They that waite vppon lyinge vanities (that is, which depende vppon any thinge ſaue God alone) forſake their owne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie) 1. they refuſe their owne felicitie, and that goodneſſe which they ſhould other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe receaue of GOD. Wherefore let euerie one of vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> take firſt into his heart, and then into his mouth the words of the Pſalmiſt ſayinge to Almightie GOD. Whome haue <hi>I</hi> in heauen but thee? And <hi>I</hi> haue deſired none in earth with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12417:6"/>Thus hitherto it appeareth that Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on belongeth to the Lord onely. And by that which next enſueth it ſhall be manifeſt that Gods helpe alone is ſufficient for vs. For when the Lord in <hi>Jſayes</hi> times percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued all things to be out of order, both in the Church and the Common-wealth, namely that iudgement was turned backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Iſay. 59.14 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> &amp; iuſtice ſtood farre of, that truth was fallen in the ſtreet, and equitie could not enter, and that hee which refrained from euill, made himſelfe a praye, and therewithall that noe man offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to rectifie thoſe abuſes, then Gods own arme did ſaue it, and his righteouſnes it ſelfe did ſuſtaine it.<note place="margin">Iſay. 63, 1.3 4 5</note> And when as the day of vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt the <hi>Edomites</hi> came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of the Lord, and the day of his redeemed was come, then he trod the wine preſſe alone, his owne arme helped him, and his wrath it ſelfe ſuſtained him. And when as <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſay. 26.1.</note> Saluation ſhall God ſet vp for walles and bulwarkes: his meaning was to ſignifie that Gods protection and defence ſhould be ſufficient for vs:<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.6, 3.</note> whereupon it is that <hi>Dauid</hi> in this preſent Pſalme will not be afraide of ten thouſand of the people,
<pb facs="tcp:12417:6"/>
that ſhould beſet him round about, becauſe God is his buckler and the lifter vp of his head. And as it is teſtified in the 23. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23 4.1.</note> though he ſhould walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, yet would he feare no euill, becauſe the Lord is his ſhepheard, whoſe rod and ſtaffe doe comfort him. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, by <hi>Salomons</hi> determination,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note> the name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the righteous runneth vnto it, and is exalted. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (as it is in <hi>Zacharie</hi>)<note place="margin">Zech. 2.4.5.</note> may be inhabited with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out walles, if the Lord bee vnto her a wall of fire round about her, and the glorie in the middes of her. And if the Lord be with <hi>Judah,</hi> in the ſiege againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then ſhall <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> bee a cup of poyſon to all the people round about,<note place="margin">Zech. 12.2, 3.</note> yea it ſhall be an heauie ſtone for all people. All that lift it vp ſhalbe torne, though all the people of the earth be gathered together againſt it. And when as <hi>Saneherib</hi> inuaded the land of <hi>Jury,</hi> with a moſt populous and puiſſant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to make an abſolute conqueſt of it, the ſubſtance,<note place="margin">2 Chron, 32.7 8.</note> of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his militarie oration was this. Be ſtrong and couragious: feare not, neither be afraid, for the king of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> neither for al the multitude that is with him,
<pb facs="tcp:12417:7"/>
for there be more with vs, then is with him. With him is an arme of fleſh (that is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of man,) but with vs is the Lorde our God for to help vs, &amp; to fight our battailes.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, though Saluation be of the Lord, yet the ordinarie meanes of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation appointed by God are not to bee neglected:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.18.</note> Wherefore <hi>Dauid</hi> was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner entred into his kingdome, but hee gaue commandement that the children of <hi>Judah</hi> ſhould be taught to ſhoot, leaſt they ſhould haue beene ouermatched by their enemies the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> in that art of warfare.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.31.</note>And when <hi>Abſalom</hi> rebelled againſt him, he did not onely pray earneſtly, that God would turne the Counſel of <hi>Ahitophel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fooliſhnes: but alſo hee ſent his friend <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite,</hi> into the armie of <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> to be his diſcouerer from thence of all principal and dangerous plots &amp; deſignes,<note place="margin">verſ, 34.35, 36.37.</note> and that he might ſkilfully bring the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Ahitophel</hi> to naught, the which hee deemed more perillous vnto him then all <hi>Abſaloms</hi> forces.<note place="margin">2. king. 9.16 28 &amp; 10.11.14</note> King <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo that he might not want the ſinewes of warre, nor the ornaments of peace vſed traffike with his Nauie, by the way of the red Sea, to
<pb facs="tcp:12417:7"/>
fetch gold fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ophir</hi> in abundance,<note place="margin">verſe. 27.</note> wherby he was enabled to giue ſiluer in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as ſtones.<note place="margin">1. king. 10.16 17</note> And his armory gliſtered with 200. targets, &amp; 300. ſhieldes of beaten gold. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he prepared 1400. Chariots. 12000.<note place="margin">1. king. 10.26. &amp; 2 chron. 9.25</note> horſemen, and 40000. horſes for ſeruice, which were beſtowed in the Chariot cities, and with himſelfe at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder at the exceeding great war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like preparation,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 17.13, to the end.</note> which <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all dangers the 2. of the <hi>Chronicles</hi> and the 17. chapter. Such diſcouerie of the Counſels and plots of forraine enemies,<note place="margin">2. king 6, 8. to the 14.</note> as <hi>Eliſha</hi> made by diuine inſpiration vnto <hi>Jehoram,</hi> muſt now be ſupplied by intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencers abroad. How could <hi>Dauid</hi> haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded the furie of <hi>Saul,</hi> if he had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued from <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and <hi>Michol,</hi>
               <note place="margin">i. Sam. 19.1, 2. &amp; 20.</note> infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his cruell purpoſes, and eſcaped by flight? And indeede this was the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of <hi>Gedalah</hi> the gouernour, and it coſt him his life in the end,<note place="margin">Ier. 40 4.14 15, 16. &amp; 41.12,</note> for that he would not beleeue the report of <hi>Johanan</hi> who tolde him that <hi>Jſhmael</hi> meant to murther him by the inſtigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Baalis</hi> the king of the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites.</hi> Let vs enter into conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how
<pb facs="tcp:12417:8"/>
expedient it is &amp; neceſſarie to haue, &amp; to cheriſh in a kingdom and common-wealth not onely valourous men, but alſo wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iuſt men, ſuch as be feruent in prayer and interceſſion for the publike good, &amp; thoſe that bee forward to execute lawes againſt malefactours. As for valorous men, howe ſhould the <hi>Jſraelites</hi> haue beene deliuered out of the hands of the <hi>Midianites,</hi> had it not beene for the ſword of the Lord, and of <hi>Gideon?</hi> They had ſtill laine vnder the yoke of <hi>Cuſhan Riſhathaim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 7, 20</note> King of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> vnleſſe <hi>Othniel</hi> had beene raiſed vpp a ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vnto them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 3.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ehud</hi> ſaued them out of the handes of the <hi>Moabites:</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 15.</note> And <hi>Shamgar</hi> and <hi>Samſon</hi> from the <hi>Philistines:</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Barak</hi> likewiſe deliuered them from <hi>Iabin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 14 &amp; 15. &amp;. 16</note> the King of <hi>Canaan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. cap. 4.</note> and <hi>Jphtah</hi> from the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites.</hi> And the Lord wrought a great Saluation for all <hi>Jſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. cap. 12.</note> when <hi>Dauid</hi> ſlewe <hi>Goliah</hi> the <hi>Philiſtine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.5.</note> Concerning wiſe men, how neceſſarie they be in euerie ſtate, <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> implyeth when hee ſaith in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, I</hi> haue ſeene this wiſedom vnder the ſunne,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.13.14 15.16.18.</note> and it is great vnto me: A little Cittie, and few men in it, and a great King came againſt
<pb facs="tcp:12417:8"/>
it, and compaſſed it about, &amp; builded fortes againſt it: and there was founde therein a poore and wiſe man, and hee deliuered the Citie by his wiſedome. So was the City of <hi>Abel</hi> preſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rage of <hi>Joab</hi> by the wiſedome of one woman,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20.13. to the 23.</note> who perſwaded the Citizens to deliuer the head of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious traytour <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri.</hi> And touching Iuſt men, <hi>I</hi> haue learned of <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the <hi>Temanite</hi> in the booke of <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 22.30.</note> that the innocent ſhall deliuer the Iland, and it ſhall be preſerued by the pureneſſe of his hands: ſo that if but ten iuſt men had beene founde in <hi>Sodom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.32.</note> the Cittie ſhould haue beene ſpared for their ſakes.<note place="margin">Gen. 19, 22, 20 21.</note> Neither would the Angell deſtroy <hi>Sodom</hi> till <hi>Lot</hi> was departed thence into a place of ſafety, the which at his requeſt was kept from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction:<note place="margin">Act. 27.22.23.</note> And in a moſt ſtormy tempeſt vpon the midland ſea, God gaue vnto <hi>Paul</hi> the liues of all that ſayled with him. When King <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſaide with teares in his eyes to <hi>Eliſha</hi> lying vpon his death bed,<note place="margin">2 King. 13.14.</note> O my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my father, the Chariot of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; the horſemen of the ſame, he ſignified that the Kingdome had beene more proſpered by
<pb facs="tcp:12417:9"/>
his prayers, then by force of armes. And God in his iuſt wrath had vtterly conſumed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the caſe of the golden Calfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.23.</note> had not <hi>Moſes</hi> his choſen ſtood in the breach before him, to turne away his anger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.41. to the end.</note>And they had at another time altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther periſhed for murmuring vpon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of rebellious <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and not <hi>Aaron</hi> made an atonement for them. Miſerable then and wretched was the ſtate of the Iewes,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.16.</note> when as <hi>Jeremie</hi> was commanded not to pray for them: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as God himſelf proteſted, that though <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtoode before him,<note place="margin">Ier, 15:1.</note> yet his affection could not bee toward that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>And as for round executing of Iuſtice vpon offenders,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note> the great neceſſitie therof appeareth hereby, becauſe it is directly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the wordes of the Preacher, that the onely delay of Iuſtice is the anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of tranſgreſſours. Wherefore King <hi>Dauid</hi> made a ſolemne promiſe that hee would betimes deſtroy all the wicked of the Land,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>01.8.</note> that hee might cut of all the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb facs="tcp:12417:9"/>
of iniquitie, from the citie of the lord. And for the ſame reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> in the Canticles: Take vs the Foxes, the little Foxes, which deſtroy the vines.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> Which courſe if we had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many yeares ago with the Ieſuites, ſecular Prieſts, and other ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie men, we had not been ſo peſtered with them, and endangered by them, as nowe we are, and of late haue beene.<note place="margin">Deut. 13.11. &amp; 17.13.</note> Wherefore it is high time to put hand to this work, that all <hi>Jſrael</hi> may heare &amp; feare &amp; do no more preſumptuouſly. Thus then it is euident that there is great vſe and neede of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie meanes of preſeruation, the want whereof maketh a verie wofull eſtate. As whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord of hoſtes meant in the time of <hi>Iſay</hi> to expoſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> to all inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, both oppreſſions and miſeries at home, and alſo inuaſions abroad, then he threatned, that he would take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Jeruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 3.1.2.3.</note> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Judah</hi> the ſtay &amp; the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, euen all the ſtay of bread &amp; all the ſtay of water, the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man, &amp; the man of war, the Iudg &amp; the Prophet, the prudent, &amp; the aged, the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of fiftie, and the honourable, and the Counſeller, and the cunning artificer, and thy eloquent man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12417:10"/>Now that Saluation is of the Lorde wee haue had good experience of late by the rare manner of the diſcouering of that damnable and diueliſh deuiſe which ſhould haue beene acted, vpon the fift of Nouember laſt. For the ſame God which inſpired <hi>Eliſha</hi> that hee could tell the King of <hi>Jſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 6.12</note> euen the verie wordes which the king of <hi>Aram</hi> ſpake in his priuie chamber: And who in the dayes of <hi>Amos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 3.7.</note> would doe nothing, but he reuealed his ſecrets vnto his ſeruants the Prophets: And who appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to <hi>Joſeph</hi> in a dreame ſayd.<note place="margin">Math. 2.13.</note> Ariſe and take the babe and his mother, and flee into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and be there till I bring thee word, for <hi>Herode</hi> will ſeeke the babe to deſtroy him.<note place="margin">Pſ. 91.3.5.6.</note> And who promiſeth in the 91. <hi>Pſalme</hi> to deliuer the faithfull, not onely from the noyſome peſtilence, but alſo from the ſnare of the hunter, not onely from the arrowe that flyeth by day, but alſo from the terrour of the night, not onely from the plague that deſtroyeth at noonetide, but alſo from the peſtilence that walketh in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: euen he the ſame God, put into the head of our gracious Soueraigne, to make
<pb facs="tcp:12417:10"/>
an vncouth and ſtrang conſtruction of an vnſubſcribed letter, but yet ſuch an one as whereby both he and his, and all wee were wondrouſly deliuered from the greateſt daunger that euer would haue befallen vs.</p>
            <p>And that it may otherwiſe alſo appeare that this our Saluation was of the Lorde, conſider with what intent the letter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid was written, namely to ſaue one friend from periſhing among vs, but this reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being ſtill holden that wee ſhould haue receiued the terrible intended blow. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, Almighty God, who by his infinite po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and wiſedome bringeth light out of darkeneſſe, and life out of death:<note place="margin">Iſay. 45.1.</note> and who made <hi>Cyprus</hi> his annointed holding and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his right hand to ſubdue nations for the deliuerie of his people out of the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of <hi>Babilon,</hi> whereas <hi>Cyrus</hi> at the firſt meant nothing leſſe, but only thought ther by to ſatiſfie his owne ambition, vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, auarice, and crueltie: and who alſo turned the treachery of <hi>Iudas</hi> to the Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind:<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> euen hee the ſame God of his vnſpeakeable goodneſſe made vſe of
<pb facs="tcp:12417:11"/>
this vndated letter intended for the good of one man onely, to the preſeruation of vs al both Prince and people.</p>
            <p>Moreouer the greatnes of our deliuerance may appeare by this, that the conſpiracie went forward, and our daunger continued without perfite diſcouerie, till within few houres of the appointed time wherein the cruell maſſacre ſhould haue been put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. So <hi>Pharaoh</hi> brought the <hi>Jſraelites</hi> into ſuch ſtraytes,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.21, 22.</note> he being with his army behind them, that if the Sea, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, had not giuen preſent way vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, they had been al put to the ſword, man, woman, and child. Likewiſe <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was ſo diſtreſſed by <hi>Saneheribs</hi> armie that he confeſſed it to be a day of tribulation,<note place="margin">Iſay. 37.3.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buke and blaſphemie: for the children were come to the birth, &amp; there was no ſtrength to bring forth. In ſo much as <hi>Hezekia</hi> and his people muſt needs haue beene deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnleſſe the Lorde had ſodainely put an hooke in <hi>Saneheribs</hi> noſtrils and a bridle in his lips,<note place="margin">verſe. 29.36.</note> and had cauſed his Angell to ſlay foureſcore and fiue thouſand of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies armie in the ſpace of one night.<note place="margin">Pſa 11.6.3.</note> When <hi>Dauid</hi> made this mone in the 116. Pſalme,
<pb facs="tcp:12417:11"/>
that the ſnares of death compared him, and the griefes of the graue caught hold on him his meaning was to ſignifie in what great danger he had beene in the wilderneſſe of <hi>Maon,</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> and his armie compaſſed him and his followers round about to take them, ſo that they could not poſſiblie haue eſcaped the edge of the ſword,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 23 26.27.</note> if there had not come by Gods prouidence an vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for meſſenger to <hi>Saul</hi> in poſt, ſaying, Haſt thee and come, for the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> haue inuaded the land. Vndoubtedly <hi>Jehoſhua</hi> was brought neere to the point of his vtter vndoing ſeeing it is ſayd of him:<note place="margin">Zech. 3.2. Pſa. 68.20.</note> Is not this a firebrand taken out of the fire? Thus our God to whom belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth the iſſues of death hath infinite meanes to deliuer his in the greateſt and moſt extreame daungers, that we may know that Saluation belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord. Again that this our late preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be acknowledged to haue come of the Lord onely, call to minde what our doings and deſerts were at that time &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: ſurely I feare greatly, leaſt if the Lord had viſited vs,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> as in the day of <hi>Zephaniah</hi> hee ſearched <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with lightes, hee ſhould haue founde many frozen in
<pb facs="tcp:12417:12"/>
their dregs, that is, by their proſperitie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened in their wickedneſſe, and ſaying in their hearts the Lord wil neither doe good not euill. Hee ſhould (I feare) haue found many drawing iniquitie with the cordes of vanitie, and ſinne as it were with cart-ropes: putting far away the euil day,<note place="margin">Iſay. 5.18.</note> approaching to the ſeat of iniquitie. Wherfore in this reſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pect we may ſay with the Prophet <hi>Jeremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.3. Lam 3.22.</note> It is the Lordes mercies that wee were not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions faile not. And all this Saluation came vnto vs from the Lord for the Goſpels ſake which wee profeſſe, leaſt our enemies by their good ſucceſſe in this attempt, ſhould haue taken occaſion to haue blaſphemed the name of God, ſaying where is now the God of the Proteſtants?</p>
            <p>But indeede one motiue of the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours to encreaſe their hope of good ſucceſſe in this wicked enterpriſe, was this conceit, that they ſuppoſed that God had giuen vs ouer for our ſins, as may appeare by thoſe words of the vndated letter for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly named, God &amp; man haue concurred to puniſh the wickednes of this time. This
<pb facs="tcp:12417:12"/>
ſelfe ſame opinion encouraged <hi>Dauids</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries in this preſent Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 3 2.</note> as is colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the words of the ſecond verſe, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſay to my ſoule, there is no helpe for him in God. And likewiſe, in the 71. Pſalme, <hi>Dauids</hi> enemies ſpake of him, and they that laid wait for his ſoule, tooke their Counſell together, ſaying, God hath forſaken him, perſue &amp; take him, for there is none to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him. This alſo was the cunning and machiauellian tricke of <hi>Saneherib,</hi> which he practiſed to terrifie <hi>Hezekiah</hi> with all, when he ſaid: Am I now come vp without the lord to this land to deſtroy it? The Lord ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me,<note place="margin">Iſay 36.10.</note> goe vp againſt this land &amp; deſtroye it. Thus the late complotters pretended the name of GOD to deceaue withall, as though God had ordained them to be the rodde of his wrath in puniſhing of vs, and that the ſtaffe in their hand had beene his indignation againſt vs.<note place="margin">Iſay. 10.5.</note> But let them aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Eſdras.</hi> Are the deeds of <hi>Babylon,</hi> better then they of <hi>Zion?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Eſdras 3.31.</note> Wee deſerued deſtruction I confeſſe, but not by the hands of them whoſe life is noe better, &amp; whoſe religion is far worſe then ours. I
<pb facs="tcp:12417:13"/>
may ſay of <hi>Rome,</hi> nowe as <hi>Jſai</hi> ſometime ſpake of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> How is the faithful Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie become an Harlot?<note place="margin">Iſay. 1.21.22.</note> thy ſiluer is become droſſe, thy wine is mixt with water. God had not ſold vs into their hands,<note place="margin">1. King. 21.25.</note> becauſe they had ſolde themſelues to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe in the ſight of the Lorde as did <hi>Ahab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 73.1.</note>And ſeeing that their purpoſe was defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by diuine prouidence, and we were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the ſnare which they priuily layd for vs, therefore we may ſay and ſing, yet God is good vnto <hi>Jſrael,</hi> euen to the pure in heart. Verely if we had beene alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deſtitute of Good men as they falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagined, we had aſſuredly periſhed with fire-worke from below, as <hi>Sodom</hi> for want of ten iuſt men in it was deſtroyed with a raine of brimſtone from aboue. But yet ſome <hi>Lot</hi> (prayſed be God) remaineth in the Citie among vs to keepe vs from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet ſome <hi>Paul</hi> ſayleth in the ſhippe with vs to keepe vs from drowning,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.14. verſe. 22. Act 27.24.25. Pſal. 106.23.</note> yet ſome <hi>Moſes</hi> is founde ſtandinge in the breach to turne away Gods wrath from vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12417:13"/>And there is yet ſome <hi>Aaron</hi> left to make an atonement for vs. Yet, <hi>I</hi> ſaie, ſome <hi>Noes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.46. to the 51. Ezech. 14.14.16.20. &amp; Ier 15.1.</note> or <hi>Jobs,</hi> or <hi>Samuels,</hi> or <hi>Daniels</hi> haue their being amongſt vs, whoſe praiers are ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall for themſelues and vs likewiſe. And ſo we finde ſaluation from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Good Lord what lenitie went before on the behalfe of the Kings Maieſtie and the ſtate, and what crueltie was like to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued on the partes of the conſpiratours? Heereby we ſee by experience the truth of that which we reade in the Prophet Iſaie:<note place="margin">Iſay. 26 10.</note> let mercie be ſhewed to the wicked yet hee will not learne righteouſneſſe, in the land of vprightneſſe will he doe wickedlie, and will not behold the Maieſtie of the Lorde. Though <hi>Dauid</hi> played with his hand vpon the harpe before <hi>Saule</hi> to mitigate the rage of the euill ſpirite that was vpon him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.9.10</note> yet <hi>Saule</hi> intended to ſmite <hi>Dauid</hi> to the wall with the ſpeare which he held in his hand.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.4 to the 9 &amp; 26.7.8.9.20.</note> Yea though <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpared the life of <hi>Saul,</hi> when he had him twiſe in his hands to ſtabbe him, or to diſpoſe of him at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet for all that <hi>Saul</hi> continually purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, as one would ſeeke a flea or hunt a
<pb facs="tcp:12417:14"/>
Partriche in the mountaines.</p>
            <p>Thus the traytours would haue recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced the Kings lenitie with extreame cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie; for if they had proſpered in their moſt miſchieuous intendement, they meant to haue killed the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me with the yong: They purpoſed to meete vs as a beare robbed of her whelpes:<note place="margin">Deut. 22.6. Prou. 17.12. Hab. 1.8.</note> wee ſhould haue found &amp; felt them more fierce then the wolues in the euening. As they of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> threſhed <hi>Gilead</hi> with threſhing inſtruments of yron: and as they of <hi>Tyrus</hi> ſhut the whole capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie in <hi>Edom:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 2.3.9.11.13.</note> and as <hi>Edom</hi> purſued his brother with the ſworde, caſting of all pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and his anger ſpoyled him euermore, and his wrath watched him alway: and as the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> ript vp the women with child of <hi>Gilead,</hi> that they might enlarge their owne border: euen ſo for al the world would theſe tygerlike men haue dealt with vs. <hi>Adonibezek</hi> cut of the thumbs of the hands and feet of his captiues, and made them to gather bread vnder his table:<note place="margin">Iud. 1.7.</note> yet, hee ſuffred them to liue.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Naaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> would make
<pb facs="tcp:12417:14"/>
no couenant with them of <hi>Jabeſh Gilead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 11.2.</note> except he might thruſt out their right eies, and ſo bring that ſhame vppon <hi>Jſrael:</hi> yet was he content that they ſhould enioy their liues. But if theſe blood-thirſtie men, (ſome wherof are alreadie cut of by iuſtice not hauing liued out halfe their dayes) had come to the full period of their hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, ſhould haue beene hearde ſoundinge in our eares but kill and ſlay.<note place="margin">Prouerb. 12.10.</note> Thus euen the mindes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are cruell; but ſtill Saluation is of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Theſe vnderminers of the ſtate ſaid hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily of vs one to another, let vs breake their bonds and take their cordes from vs:<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.</note> but hee that dwelleth in the heauen did laugh: the Lorde had them in diriſion. They ſaid perhaps among themſelues by imitation of the 83. Pſalme. Come let vs cutte them of from beeing a Nation, and let the name of the Caluiniſts bee noe more in remembraunce. Let vs take their habitations for our poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:<note place="margin">Pſa. 83 4 12.13, 16: 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12417:15"/>But our God hath made them like vnto a wheele, and as the ſtuble before the wind, he hath filled their faces with ſhame, that they may knowe, that hee which is called <hi>Jehouah</hi> is alone, euen the moſt high o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the earth. They reſemble <hi>Ephraim</hi> and the inhabitants of <hi>Samaria,</hi> which ſaide in the pride and preſumption of their heart. The bricks are fallen but we wil build it with hewen ſtones,<note place="margin">Iſay 9.9.10.11.12,</note> the wild figge trees are cut downe, but wee will change them into Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars: neuertheleſſe, the Lorde will raiſe vp the aduerſaries of <hi>Rezin</hi> againſt him, and ioyne his enemies together: <hi>Aram</hi> before, and the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> behind, and they ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure <hi>Jſrael</hi> with open mouth. They had no doubt as high and proud a conceite as poſſeſſed <hi>Benhadad,</hi> when he ſaid, the gods doe ſo to me, and more alſo,<note place="margin">1 King 20.10 11.</note> if the duſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> bee enoughe for all the people that follow mee for euerie man an handfull, but let not him that girdeth his harneſſe boaſt himſelfe, as hee that putteth it of. For SALVATION belongeth vnto the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now then for ſomuch as no man doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,
<pb facs="tcp:12417:15"/>
and euerie man confeſſeth, that our late deliuerance out of exceeding great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger proceeded from the Lord, lette vs firſt of all be admoniſhed to be thankefull vnto Almightie God, by the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who after that hee had eſcaped the perill of the Court of <hi>Achiſh,</hi> ſolemnely promiſed in the 34. Pſalme, that he would alwaies giue thankes vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſa. 34 1.</note> and that the prayſe of God ſhold be continually in his mouth. And likewiſe by the example of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 20.26</note> who after that famous victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie againſt the vnited forces of <hi>Ammon, Moab,</hi> and Mount Seir, aſſembled his ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and other his ſubiectes to bleſſe the lord in that place, which was afterwarde by that occaſion called the valley of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let vs receaue admonition to be conſtant in the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpel, notwithſtanding all threats, calumniations, and dangers intended by the fraud or force of any enemies whatſoeuer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.23.51.69 85.61.25.28.83.109 entire.</note> by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Pſalmiſt in the 119. Pſalme, who, though Princes did ſitte and ſpeake againſt him, and the proud had him exceedingly in
<pb facs="tcp:12417:16"/>
deriſion, imagining a lye againſt him, and digging pits for him: yea though the bands of the wicked robbed him, and laid ſnares for him, and wayted to deſtroy him: ſo that his ſoule cleaued to the duſt, and melted for heauineſſe, and hee was like a bottell in the ſmoake, and his ſoule was continually in his hand: yet hee declined not from the law of God, nor forgat his precepts, nor ſwarued from his teſtimonies and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let vs be encouraged to hope for ſuch helpe and ſuccour in time of neede hereafter,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> for that Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day, the ſame alſo is for euer, not onely the founder but alſo the preſeruer of the Church. Hee was our arme in the morning when the Goſpell began to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in theſe parts, and he will no doubt be our ſtrength in the euening thereof vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. hee will performe his worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs,<note place="margin">Pſa. 138.7, 8.</note> and not forſake the worke of his hands. But this hope muſt be grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a prouiſo that we practiſe in life as wee profeſſe in word. And therefore I ſay to all that be here preſent as <hi>Azariah</hi> the ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:12417:16"/>
of <hi>Obed</hi> ſaid to King <hi>Aſa</hi> and all <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Beniamin:</hi> Heare yee me, the Lord is with you, while you bee with him:<note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.1.</note> and if yee ſeeke him, hee will bee found of you, but if yee forſake him, hee will forſake you. Bee it farre from vs to runne the race of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and obſtinacie, till our wickedneſſe be full as the <hi>Amorites</hi> was,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.16.</note> when the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> came to invade them. Be it farre from vs, who haue lately receaued ſo great a Saluation from the Lorde,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.16</note> to mocke the meſſengers of God, and deſpiſe his wordes and miſuſe his Prophets, vntil the wrath of the Lord ſhould ariſe againſt vs, and till there were noe remedie but that GOD muſt needes puniſh our ſinnes in his iuſt and heauie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, let vs be exhorted to fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vigilancie againſt the priuie prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of the Romiſh faction at home and abroad. Remember that when <hi>Ahab</hi> had ouerthrowen <hi>Ben-hadad</hi> in one ſette bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, hee was aduertiſed by a Prophet to bee of good courage,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 20.22</note> but yet to
<pb facs="tcp:12417:17"/>
take heede what hee did, becauſe the King of <hi>Aram</hi> when the yeare was gone about wold come vp againſt him the ſecond time. But ſurely the Ieſuites and their conſorts will not giue vs ſo long a breathing time. For they are like the raging Sea,<note place="margin">Iſay. 57.20.21.</note> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſt, whoſe waters caſt vp mire and dirt. It would ſeeme that they are imitators of thoſe euill and cruell men mentioned in the iii. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſa. 111.22.</note> which imagine euill things in their heart, and make warre continually. To vs they are ſtrangers from the wombe. Can the blacke <hi>Moore</hi> chang his ſkinne,<note place="margin">Pſa. 58.3. Ier. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.23.</note> or the <hi>Leopard</hi> his ſpots? Then may theſe men alſo do good which are accuſtomed to do euill.</p>
            <p>Heere I cannot omitte the ſentence in the 76. Pſalme, where is ſetfoorth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, and care for the defence of his people of <hi>Jeruſlem,</hi> in the deſtruction of the Armie of <hi>Sancherib:</hi> The words, being directed to Almightie God, ſtand thus in the text:<note place="margin">Pſa. 76.10.</note> Surely the rage of man ſhall turne to thy praiſe: the remnant of the rage ſhalt thou reſtraine. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo in this late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracy ſuch hath beene the euent that the rage of
<pb facs="tcp:12417:18"/>
the conſpirators hath turned to the prayſe of God, who in his iuſt iudgement hath cauſed them to fall into the pit which they made and digged themſelues:<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.15.16.</note> procuring their miſchiefe to returne vppon their owne head, and their crueltie to fall vpon their owne pate.<note place="margin">Exod, 9.i6.</note> GOD ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his power in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and declared his name throughout all the world by his ouerthrow.<note place="margin">Hab. 2.14.</note> Likewiſe in the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> the earth was filled with the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters couer the Sea.<note place="margin">Iſay. 26.9.</note> And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſuch iudgements of God are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world ſhall learne righteouſneſſe. Thus by this late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie God is magnified, and the eyes of many, (I truſt) are opened to ſee, that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and the reſt of the Romiſh brood are more daungerous gueſts to the ſtate, then formerly they had beleeued.</p>
            <p>But yet the remnant of their rage muſt be reſtrained, vnder Gods prouidence, by circumſpection &amp; foreſight of the Church and common-wealth watchmen, by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb facs="tcp:12417:19"/>
and truſtie inquiſition, and by vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall &amp; vndelayed execution of lawes, which is the verie life of the lawes. And if all the premiſſes be obſerued, then they that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to bring in and erect poperie, ſhall be found the builders of <hi>Babell</hi> to their owne confuſion:<note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> And they ſhall bee ſubiect to the curſe which fell on <hi>Hiel</hi> the <hi>Bethelite</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the reedifying of <hi>Jericho,</hi> who layd the foundation thereof in <hi>Abiram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 16.34.</note> his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne, and ſet vp the gates thereof in his yongeſt ſon <hi>Segub.</hi> Then <hi>I</hi> ſay, ſhal their caſe nothing differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of the ofſpring of <hi>Eſau,</hi> of whome God ſpeaketh thus in <hi>Malachy.</hi> Though <hi>Edom</hi> ſay we are impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, but wee will returne and build the deſolate places, yet ſaith the Lorde of Hoſtes, they ſhall build but I will deſtroy it,<note place="margin">Malach. 1.4.</note> and they ſhall call them the border of wickedneſſe and the people with whom the Lord is angrie for euer. And it ſhall bee ſaide of them, and their workes, as <hi>Habacuk</hi> ſpeaketh: Beholde, is it not of the Lord of Hoſtes, that the people ſhall labour in the verie fire?<note place="margin">Hab. 2.13.</note> the people
<pb facs="tcp:12417:19"/>
ſhall euen wearie themſelues with verie va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. They and their deuiſes ſhall conſume like a ſnayle that melteth, and like the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely fruite of a woman that hath not ſeene the ſunne.<note place="margin">Pſa. 58.8.9.</note> As raw fleſh is taken out of the pot, before the water feele the fire of thornes, ſo ſhall God deſtroy their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes before they can be effected: yea they ſhall be as the graſſe on the houſe toppes,<note place="margin">Pſ. 129.6.7.</note> which withereth afore it commeth foorth: wherof the mower filleth not his hand, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the gleaner his lap.<note place="margin">Pſa. 7.14.</note> Then they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed trauaile with wickedneſſe hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued miſchiefe, but they ſhall bring forth a lye; they may purpoſe to hatch the cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice egges, but they ſhall onely weaue the Spiders webbe. And hereof wee haue a ſtronge and ſtedfaſt hope,<note place="margin">Iſay. 59.5.</note> becauſe that as well the deſtruction of the wicked, as the Saluation of the Godly proceedeth from the Lord, whoſe bleſſing is vppon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, accordinge to the latter part of this text. And thy bleſſing is vppon thy people. Beholde, and conſider
<pb facs="tcp:12417:20"/>
the humilitie, modeſtie, and ſinceritie of <hi>Dauid:</hi> For if danger be imminent to the ſtate, then hee caſteth all the imputation thereof vpon himſelfe ſaying,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.17.</note> I haue ſinned, yea I haue done wickedly: but theſe ſheepe what haue they done? let thine hand I pray thee, be againſt me and againſt my fathers houſe. But on the other ſide when as he is here deliuered from extreame danger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he aſcribeth his deliuerance to Gods fauour toward his people, ſaying to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, with eyes and heart lifted vp to heauen, And thy bleſſing is vppon thy people.</p>
            <p>Alſo when <hi>Dauid</hi> was falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by Chuſh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.6.7.</note> one of <hi>Sauls</hi> kinſmen, he called vnto God for helpe, framing his prayer in this wiſe. Ariſe O Lorde in thy wrath, and lift vp thy againſt the rage of mine enemies, and awake for me accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iudgement that thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed So ſhall the congregation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe thee about: for their ſakes returne on high (that is, declare thy power for thy Churches ſake.)</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12417:20"/>Vpon whome falleth Gods bleſſing? ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely vpon Gods people.</p>
            <p>Therefore we muſt firſt ſhew our ſelues to be Gods people, &amp; then we may expect the encreaſe and continuance of Gods bleſſing. For the accompliſhing whereof,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.16.</note> let our light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good workes,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9. Tit. 2.14.</note> and glorifie our father which is in heauen, acknowledging vs to be a choſen generation, a royal prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, an holy Nation, a peculiar people, zealous of good workes, ſhewing forth the vertues of him, that hath called vs out of darknes into his maruailous light.<note place="margin">Pſa. 21, 3.6.</note> And then we may haue an aſſured hope, that God will preuent our King with liberall bleſſings, &amp; ſet him as bleſſings for euer, making him a perpetuall example of his fauour to this preſentage, &amp; to all poſteritie. Then <hi>I</hi> ſay, we may conceaue good hope, that God wil endue all of vs with conuenient bleſſings both ſpirituall and temporall, ſo that wee may liue in the feare of GOD, and die in his fauour, to bee partakers of the ioyes of Heauen prepared for vs,
<pb facs="tcp:12417:21"/>
by the mediation of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to whome with the father and the holy ghoſt be all honour and glorie, both now and for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
